<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Techjournal</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Techjournal</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thinking Mathematically: Chapter 4 Solutions</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/thinking-mathematically-furniture/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/thinking-mathematically-furniture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;furniture&#34;&gt;Furniture&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[!info] Furniture&#xA;A very heavy armchair needs to be moved, but the only possible movement is to rotate it through 90 degrees about any of its corners. Can it be moved so that it is exactly beside its starting position and facing the same way?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;attack&#34;&gt;Attack&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Checkerboard your floor&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tile the floor with big squares of size = 0.5 x chair-width&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Colour them using green and yellow&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Initial and target colours&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Start square: suppose the four legs of the chair sits on the four tiles creating a &lt;code&gt;2x2&lt;/code&gt; block.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Target square: one chair width to the right.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[!info] Conjecture: Rotation preserves square colour&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Part 1: The World of Subsequences, Longest Increasing Subsequence</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/subsequences-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/subsequences-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Awhile ago I came across an interesting programming exercise at work. There is an external system that is integrated with our application. There are several API calls being made to it, one of which requires setting a password field. The external system enforces a set of rules for acceptable passwords. There are the usual rules such as a password cannot be the user&amp;rsquo;s phone number, or the reversed old password and so on. But there is a rule that caught my attention, it states:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Part 2: The World of Subsequences, Longest Increasing Subsequence</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/subsequences-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/subsequences-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the previous article we showed the algorithm for finding the longest continuously increasing subsequence. Now, we try to find the longest increasing subsequence and drop the contiguous requirement. First we begin with a formal definition of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[!info] Algorithm Description&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description:&lt;/strong&gt; Given a sequence of n elements a1 a2 a3…ana1​ a2​ a3​…an​, find the longest continuously increasing &lt;em&gt;subsequence&lt;/em&gt;. A &lt;em&gt;subsequence&lt;/em&gt; is any subset of the elements taken in order, of the form ai1 ai2…aikai1​​ ai2​​…aik​​ where 1≤i1&amp;lt;i2&amp;lt;i3…ik≤n1≤i1​&amp;lt;i2​&amp;lt;i3​…ik​≤n. An &lt;em&gt;increasing subsequence&lt;/em&gt; is one in which the numbers are getting strictly larger, that is for every aiai​ in the subsequence we have ai&amp;gt;ai−1ai​&amp;gt;ai−1​.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer Networks Q&amp;A: CDNs</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/computer-networks-qa-cdns/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/computer-networks-qa-cdns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this article we will post questions and answers to understand the concept of CDNs and overlay networks&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-the-drawback-to-using-traditional-approach-of-having-a-single-publicly-accessible-server&#34;&gt;What is the drawback to using traditional approach of having a single, publicly accessible server?&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Geographic distance: Users are located all over the globe, there is potentially vast geographic distance between the users and the data center. When packets traverse lots of links it is possible that a link has a lower throughput resulting in increased time to travel.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Demand spikes: Popular resources such as a video can be requested many times, having a single server to repeatedly be sending the exact same data over the same communication link over and over again wastes bandwidth and it is financially costly to the content provider.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Single point of failure: In case of accidents, such as natural disaster or a massive power outage the entire data center can be taken offline.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-a-cdn&#34;&gt;What is a CDN?&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CDNs stands for &lt;strong&gt;Content Distribution Networks&lt;/strong&gt;. CDNs are networks of multiple, geographically distributed servers and/or data centers holding copies of content and serve users from a server or a server cluster that matches best to the user request. CDNs address the issues discussed above.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for Trading: Build a Decision Tree Learner</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/machine-learning-for-trading-build-a-decision-tree-learner/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/machine-learning-for-trading-build-a-decision-tree-learner/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The focus of this article is building a decision tree learner and evaluate its performance in different settings and finally compare it with a linear regression learner. The main learning goals are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervised Learning:&lt;/strong&gt; Understanding what is supervised learning and how to train, query and evaluate its performance&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decision Tree:&lt;/strong&gt; Learning how to build a decision tree and use it in different configurations&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervised-learning&#34;&gt;Supervised Learning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider a series of predictor(here predictor just means inputs) measurements xi,i=1,2,…,Nxi​,i=1,2,…,N where for each predictor there is an associated response measurement yiyi​. From a statistical point of view the goal is to usually find a fit such that we can relate the predictors to the responses as accurately as possible. This is interesting because it allows to understand the relationships between the predictors and responses and also we can use such a fit to make predictions of future values for responses given historical predictor data. Such problems where there is a series of predictor measurements and an accompanying series of response measurements belong to the supervised learning problems category.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for Trading: Optimize Portfolio</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/machine-learning-for-trading-optimize-portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/machine-learning-for-trading-optimize-portfolio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This article builds upon Part 1 and shows how portfolio stock allocations can be optimized using Python SciPy library, the primary learning goals are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portfolio Optimization:&lt;/strong&gt; Starting with an initial guess, learn how to optimize stock allocations for a portfolio and compare the results with the non-optimized case.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;problem-statement-and-solution&#34;&gt;Problem Statement and Solution&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The goal is to use an initial guess for stock allocations and then optimize the portfolio for Sharpe ratio. Starting with a few important points to frame the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for Trading: Portfolio Analysis</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/machine-learning-for-trading-portfolio-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/machine-learning-for-trading-portfolio-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This article is about using Python to analyze portfolio stocks and allocations. The primary learning goals are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portfolio Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Given a portfolio of stocks implement several metrics to evaluate the performance of a portfolio&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;portfolio-analysis&#34;&gt;Portfolio Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are several metrics that can be used to evaluate the performance of a portfolio. Here we focus on the metrics below:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daily Returns:&lt;/strong&gt; How much a price went up or down on a particular day&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cumulative Return:&lt;/strong&gt; A measure of how much the value of the portfolio has gone up from the beginning to the end&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average Daily Return:&lt;/strong&gt; Simply the mean of the daily returns&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard Deviation of Daily Return:&lt;/strong&gt; Simply the standard deviation of the daily returns&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharpe Ratio:&lt;/strong&gt; Risk adjusted return&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharpe Ratio (SR)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mario</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/mario/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/mario/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CS50 is one of the most well known and prestigious courses on computer science. The course is offered by Harvard University faculty and based on Edx it has already more than 2.8 millions enrolled students.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was going through their material on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs50.harvard.edu/x/2021/&#34;&gt;CS50x&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs50.harvard.edu/x/2021/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;, and I came across an interesting Python problem. Citing from the course materials in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs50.harvard.edu/x/2021/psets/6/&#34;&gt;Problem Set 6&lt;/a&gt;, the students are asked the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[!info] Mario&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Implement a program the prints out a double half-pyramid of a specified height.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clean Architecture: Migrations</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/the-tale-of-migrations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/the-tale-of-migrations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been working on an intensive network migration project for a Dutch enterprise. This is by far one of the most exciting and yet fearsome projects I have been involved in. The migration project involves rebuilding the clients network based on standardized and automated profiles. This brings significant benefits to the service provider as well as the client. Such benefits are for example:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Devices will run based on a standardized and harmonious configuration throughout the entire network, thus it is always possible to deduct what configuration a certain device is running. This helps tremendously for operations and troubleshooting&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Standardized profiles allows standardized and controlled changes across the network&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Configuration management becomes easier and faster&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When migrating a network, we have to introduce a momentarily outage. Now, imagine telling a multi billion euro enterprise running heavily on its network that for the migration we need to cut out your networks for a few minutes!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
